<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	  <teiHeader>
		    <fileDesc>
			      <titleStmt>
				        <title />
				        <author />
				        <sponsor />
				        <principal />
				        <respStmt>
					          <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
				               <name />
				        </respStmt>
			      </titleStmt>
			      <publicationStmt>
				        <publisher />
				        <pubPlace />
				        <authority />
			        <date cert="low" type="release">2020</date>
			      </publicationStmt>
			      <sourceDesc>
				        <biblStruct>
					          <monogr>
						            <title />
						            <author />
						            <editor role="editor" />
						            <imprint>
							              <pubPlace />
							              <publisher />
							              <date />
						            </imprint>
					          </monogr>
				        </biblStruct>
			      </sourceDesc>
		    </fileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl n="CTS">
         	
        </refsDecl>
			      <refsDecl>
				        <refState unit="book" />
				        <refState unit="line" />
			      </refsDecl>
		    </encodingDesc>
		    <profileDesc>
			      <langUsage>
				        <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
			      </langUsage>
		    </profileDesc>
		    <revisionDesc>
            <change when="" who="" />	

		    </revisionDesc>
	  </teiHeader>
	  <text xml:lang="grc">
	  	<body>
	        <comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg012.perseus-grc2:685@θανεῖν:rdgs:"> (Seidler 1813, 95. The same conjecture had been noted by Elmsley in the margin of an edition of  Euripides he owned. The conjecture dates back to about the same years as Seidler's edition. Cf. Finglass 2007 (2), 743.). In fact, the substitution would not have semantic implications, but only syntactic ones: th e accusative Αἴγισθον would be in one case the subject of θανεῖν and in the other the subject of κτανεῖν.</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0011.tlg003.perseus-grc2:822@θανεῖν:rdgs:">θανεῖν is the lesson handed down and agreed upon. Morstadt alone conjectures κτανεῖν. (Cf. Dawe 1996(3).)</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg006.perseus-grc2:661@κτανεῖν:rdgs:">Garzya 1978.</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0011.tlg005.perseus-grc2:956@κτανεῖν:rdgs:">Dawe 1996</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg015.perseus-grc2:1376@κτανεῖν-@θʼ:rdgs:">Mastronarde 1988</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg018.perseus-grc2:4@μάλα-@γῆρας:rdgs:">.  Cf. Matthiae 1824; Jouan 1983; Kovacs 2002.  )</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg006.perseus-grc2:181@τι:rdgs:">Cf. Dobree 1846, 75: 'collato Valck ad Phoen. lege τοι'.</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg012.perseus-grc2:606@τοι:rdgs:">.</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0011.tlg003.perseus-grc2:776@τοι:rdgs:"> . Conjecture is generally accepted. Hermann 1827, 376.  Cf. Kamerbeek 1953, I; Jebb 1896; Campbell 1881 II.; Lloyd Jones-Wilson 1990; Dawe 19963; Garvie 1998.</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0011.tlg003.perseus-grc2:1266@τις:rdgs:">Wright proposes the τοι correction among several other 'not offered as certainties, [...] but rather as fair possibilities'. Text and apparatus by Lloyd Jones-Wilson 1990.  Wright 1894, XXXII.</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0011.tlg005.perseus-grc2:308@τοῖς:rdgs:"> ( Hermann 1827, 458  Cf. also Dawe 19963, Lloyd Jones-Wilson 1990; conjecture is accepted by Jebb 1894 VI; Campbell 1881 II.  Kamerbeek 1974, 55.  )</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0019.tlg003.perseus-grc2:14@υἱόν:rdgs:">The Rav. 429 (R) , the oldest manuscript of Aristophanes, is dated to the second half of the 10th century and contains twice as many singular errors as the β family, a family of 21 manuscripts derived, as R, from α . The copyist of R, in this case, missed a typical syntagma of the liturgy, which he later corrected: θεὸν υἱὸν is a frequent expression to indicate the figure of Christ within the trinity (e.g. Basil. Epist. 236, 6.13-16: συνάπτοντας λέγειν- πιστεύω εἰς Θεὸν Πατέρα. Καὶ πάλιν ἐν τῇ τοῦ Υἱοῦ ὁμολογίᾳ τὸ παραπλήσιον ποιεῖν, τῷ κοινῷ συνάπτειν τὸ ἴδιον καὶ λέγειν- εἰς Θεὸν Υἱόν). ( On the code see Orsini 2011.  Olson 2002, lxxx.  )</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg002.perseus-grc2:128@διόβολον:rdgs:">Itʼs likely that this oversight was suggested to the copyist of Par. 2713 (B) by the hellish atmosphere of the passage, and perhaps also by the frequent association of the devil with the verb αἱρέω (e.g. Chrys. Hom. in Mt. PG LVIII 773, 14: τότε αὐτὸν ὁ διάβολος εἷλεν) and the action of throwing flaming darts (e.g. Bas. Hom. in Ps.., PG XXIX 248, 16: τὰ πεπυρωμένα βέλη τοῦ διαβόλου). However, the slip did not change the syntactical function of the lexeme, which remains an agreed adjective at πλῆκτρον: Christianity is inserted in the text by pure allusion, almost by automatism.</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:theogn.theogn.VERSION:1.865@θεὸς:rdgs:">The copyist of Ven. Marc. gr. 774, olim 520 (I) made a very common mistake: the uniformation of the terminology on the basis of that of one or more adjoining words. The false chord was even simpler in this case, where the modified noun was preceded by two adjectives to the plural dative. But the Christian perspective on the texts of paganism probably influenced the copyist who defined the gods ʻmoltiʼ and ʻsciocchi, uselessʼ.</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0008.tlg001.perseus-grc3:1.2@δείπνῳ:rdgs:">The long speech of the Deipnosophists is set during a banquet, which marks the tones and parts. The words λόγος and δεῖπνον often recur, juxtaposed and combined, in the last lines of par. 1 (see the highlighted parts): the two terms, not synonymic in themselves, in these particular circumstances are almost equivalent (cf. § 4). The witnesses of the epitome Par. suppl. gr. 841 (C) and Laur. LX (E) both report ἐν τῷ τῷ. The expression ἐν τῷ ἐν ἐπιδημεῖν is not attested elsewhere, although in fact the combination of verb and state complement in place would seem better to agree with a concrete noun, such as the banquet, rather than with its ʻequivalente figurativeʼ, the discourse; cf. e.g. Ath. II.1 97 30 (ἐν Δελφοῖς ἐπιδημοῦντος Φιλίππου), Ath. VIII 43 (ἐν Ἰλίῳ ἐπιδημεῖν). The exchange conceived by Kaibel may have been influenced by the fact that the verb ἐπιδημέω (Cf. Lampe 1961, 520-521 (b2-4, f)) and the noun λόγος are constantly associated in Christian theology to indicate the incarnation or descent of the Word (cf. e.g. Ath. Exp. in Ps. PMG XVII 496.11: Ὅταν γὰρ ἐπιδημήσει μοι λόγος; Eph. Pan. PMG II 278.13: ἄνωθεν ἐπεδήμησεν ὁ θεὸς Λόγος καὶ ἐλθὼν ἐσαρκώθη ἀπὸ; Eus. Comm. in Ps. PMG XXIII 692.29: ἐπεδήμει ὁ τοῦ Θεοῦ Λόγος).</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg005.perseus-grc1:arg.16@καταμαθοῦσα:rdgs:">The verb καταμανθάνω indicates a specific way of seeing . The copyist of the Laur. 3110 (O) spontaneously replaced it with a more generic verb. In a prose text, and therefore in the absence of metric constraints, it is even easier that the substitution acts according to exclusively mental mechanisms, without any graphic-phonetic relation between lemma and variant. In such a case, if O had been codex unicus, the substitution would probably have gone unnoticed</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0008.tlg001.perseus-grc3:3.79@καλούμενα:rdgs:">Book III.79 of the Deipnosophists is dedicated to the various names by which bread is designated. Expressions such as ὁ ΑΡΤΟΠΤΙΚΙΟΣ ἄρτος καλούμενος (ll. 9-10), καλεῖταί τις ἄρτος ΑΠΑΛΟΣ (l. 15), οὗτος δὲ ὁ ἄρτος λέγεται Καππαδόκιος (ll. 17-18). The copyist of the Laur. 60.1 (B), an apographer from Marciano, accustomed to the repetition of significant terms ʻchiamatoʼ, ʻdenominatoʼ, at l. 34 made a synonymic trivialisation in favour of the verb λέγω.</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0011.tlg003.perseus-grc2:594@φρονεῖν:rdgs:">Aiace responds abruptly to Tecmessa, who tries to take him to more mythical advice, claiming that ʻpensa nonsenseʼ . The text would be consistent even if he said that ʻdice nonsenseʼ . However, we would lose the construction that contrasts two verbs indicating thinking (δοκεῖς φρονεῖν, εἰ [...] νοεῖς, vv. 594-595).</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0011.tlg005.perseus-grc2:1305@δεξαίμην:rdgs:">Electra reassures her brother: she will behave according to his indications and will not make their intention of revenge prematurely manifest, because there is no victory for her if she does not also benefit Orestes. The correct lesson is certainly δεξαίμην (a similar use, for example, in Men. Sam. 422-423: οὐδʼ ἂν ἐπὶ γενέσθαι τὸ γεγονός, μὰ τοὺς θεούς, / πρᾶγμʼ ἐδεξάμην). The most exhaustive comments to the passage dwell on the fact that λεξαίμην is the result of a typical oncial error (on which see Neapʼs reverse error. II F. 9 = L and Flor. Laur. 28.25 = Fac, λελεγμένῃ for βουλοίμην to 1298 ), while βουλοίμην must be a trivialization. The fact that δεξαίμην is palaeographically similar to δεξαίμην, however, does not in itself explain the error, which is also influenced by the meaning of the sentence.</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0011.tlg005.perseus-grc2:560@λέξω:rdgs:">The conjecture of Morstadt , is defined ʻpalaeographically elegantʼ by Finglass , who however rejects it with the motivation that the repetition καὶ δὴ λέγω σοι ... λόγος ... λέξω δέ σοι is not problematic in tragedy. The error postulated by Morstadt, however, is not plausible only from a paleographic point of view: the repetition of an expression very similar to v. 558 could have acted for Echoschreibung.</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg002.perseus-grc2:425@λέγω:rdgs:">it is not meant to say that conjecture should be accepted because λέγω is a verb more ʻsempliceʼ than δείκνυμι: as already said, in many cases there are no simple and difficult words, but only lexemes whose meaning is, in a given context, more extensive or, on the contrary, more specific. Observe such a case: Admeto orders all Thessalians to join him in mourning the death of Alcesti. Par. 2713 (B) and the Laur. 3110 (O), closely related to B (to which he is united by a series of typically Byzantine errors) modify the sentence with θέλω: in this specific case, a verbum voluntatis could seem more appropriate to an order given by Admeto to his subjects. The verb λέγω is attested with the meaning of ʻordinare, tell someone to do something (τινὰ τι)ʼ: cf. e.g. Aesch. Choe. 551-552: τἄλλα δʼ ἐξηγοῦ φίλοις, / τοὺς μέν τι ποιεῖν, τοὺς δὲ μή τι δρᾶν λέγων.</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0019.tlg003.perseus-grc2:845@ἕλω:rdgs:">Pheidippides wonders what to do with Strepsiade, who seems to have gone mad: whether to have him judged mad by a court, or even to arrange his funeral. λέγω is Marc's lectio singularis. 474 (V), and represents an imperfect anagram of the certainly correct lesson. The correctness of ἕλω can be demonstrated by its coat of arms; even if it were not so, however, the verb would have the merit of being the technical word of ʻfare imprisoning someone for something (τινά τινος)ʼ, cf. Ar. Nub. 591: ἢν Κλέωνα τὸν λάρον δώρων ἑλόντες καὶ κλοπῆς. The lesson of V, instead, is perhaps slightly influenced by the next verse: the second of Pheidippides' hypotheses ends with a verbum dicendi.</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg012.perseus-grc2:633@δούλων:rdgs:">.</comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg006.perseus-grc2:419@ψέγει:rdgs:"> says Andromache. The Laur. 32, 2 (L) and the Scor. X 1 13 (Ge), together with Stob. Anth. IV 24b 19.3, with a replacement of verbum dicendi, report a text with a different meaning: those who say, without having experience, that children are everything to their parents, suffer less but have a sad, unfortunate happiness.</comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg002.perseus-grc2:697@λέγεις:rdgs:"> .(Parker 2007, 191.).</comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0011.tlg005.perseus-grc2:1423@λέγειν:rdgs:">The choir makes a judgment on Orestes and Pilad, who were stained with the murder of Clytemestra. The sentence, in the form handed down by the codices, seems elliptical; to think that after λέγειν one had to assume an aposiopesis raises doubts about the comprehensibility of the verse. Erfurd's conjecture was unanimously accepted .Hermann 1827, 539.  Hermann 1827; Jebb 1894 (which indicates a specular corruptela in Aesch. Choe. 989); Campbell 1907 (which rectifies his choice in the textʼs edition where, by defining the conjecture ʽintolerably frigidʼ, he maintained the lesson tràdita. Cf. Campbell 1873 II); Lloyd Jones-Wilson 1990; Dawe 19963; Finglass 2007 519-520 (the choir, claiming to have nothing to object to the matricide, would shape the publicʼs opinion).</comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0011.tlg005.perseus-grc2:1467@λέγω:rdgs:"> with respect to the usual sense of expression: for Egistus it would be undeniable that there was nemesis, and the vague and indirect expression would be a way of alluding to it with subtle hypocrisy. Finglass, on the contrary, chooses λέγω and objects to Dawe's comment that hypocrisy would be more effective if Egistus was reluctant to accept the godsʼ anger towards Orestes. The implications of the passage are discussed in Lloyd Jones-Wilson 1990, 75.  Jebb 1894.  Dawe 19963; Lloyd Jones-Wilson 1990, 75 attribute it to Erfurdt.  Dawe 1973, 201.  Finglass 2007, 535.</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0011.tlg005.perseus-grc2:1467@λέγω:rdgs:">) restores the correct sense of the text: Antigone's entreaty to the Choir invokes what they hold most dear at home: a son, a bride, a treasure or a deity.</comment>


			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0011.tlg003.perseus-grc2:1012@κακὸν:rdgs:">In the Heid. Pal. gr 40 (P), the presence of the verbum dicendi immediately preceding contributes to a trivialization - born almost automatically - that generates an accusative of the internal object. The relation of hyponymy is respected: probably a copyist, taking κακὸν for a noun adjective (and therefore ʻdiscorso evilʼ), replaced it with λόγον, ʻdiscorsoʼ without connotations other than those, implicit, suggested by the rest of the passage.</comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg005.perseus-grc1:514@πλόκον:rdgs:">πλόκον is a specious emendation of λόγον which B. [scil. Barrett] calls ʽabsurdʼ. How could the Nurse catch a word from Hippolytus? But the Greeks were closer to primitive feeling here - thinking of words as physical (winget etc.), spreading pollution, and folk tales tell us of disaster caused by the dropping of stray words. Cf. Segal 1993, 255 n.19 and Pharaoh 1999, 8-9 for examples of rituals involving the use of robes and locks of hair.  Barrett 1964, 255.  )</comment>


			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0011.tlg003.perseus-grc2:1268@σμικρῶν-1268@πόνων:rdgs:"> translates Stanford ( Stanford 1963, 214. ), who prints the lecture σμικρῶν λόγων . Other editors, on the other hand, have expressed doubts about the syntagma: in fact, it is attested the use of ἐπὶ with genitive to indicate a complement of manner (cf. e.g. Plat. Symp. 192 c: ἐπὶ μεγάλης σπουδῆς); σμικρός λόγος indicates a short, concise speech (cf. e.g. Soph. El. 415-416: Ηλ. λέγʼ ἀλλὰ τοῦτο. πολλά τοι σμικροὶ λόγοι / ἔσφηλαν ἤδη καὶ κατώρθωσαν βροτούς, OC 620: δόρει διασκεδῶσιν ἐκ σμικροῦ λόγου); finally, El. 414 reads ἀλλʼ οὐ κάτοιδα πλὴν ἐπὶ σμικρὸν φράσαι . However, the combination ἐπὶ σμικρῶν λόγων is problematic: Jebb, for example, considers it doubtful that in this place λόγων could mean ʻaccountsʼ, and nevertheless considers the conjecture σμικρὸν λόγον ʻhardly satisfactory when λόγον is addedʼ. J.G. Jaeger and Dawe tried to solve the difficulty by introducing another bisyllable that was satisfactory for the meaning. ( Cf. Hermann 1827; Campbell 1873 II; Kamerbeek 1953 I, 240.  Jebb 1896, 188-189.  Reiske's conjecture is accepted by Lloyd Jones-Wilson 1990, 37-38; Garvie 1998, 240.  Jaeger 1811, 163.  )</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0011.tlg007.perseus-grc2:66@λόγος:rdgs:">the words mean ʽhas the people a say?ʼ), Guidorizzi 2008 and defended by Pearson 1925, 156.).</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0593.1st1K001.1st1K-grc1:14.1@λόγου:rdgs:">The manuscript tradition of Elena's Consortium is bipartite: in Burn. 95 (Crisippianus) (A) opposes a group of β manuscripts of which the γ, δ, ζ subfamilies are part. Therefore, the λόγου lesson is confirmed, at least on an archetypal level, by the coat of arms. The concept of λόγος is fundamental within the Gorgian work: its discussion occupies paragraphs 8-14, a third of the work, and the λόγος δυνάστης μέγας μέγας (8. 3) is famous. By the term, Gorgia refers to any kind of verbal production, from the arringe of a trial to scientific (13.1-2: τοὺς τῶν μετεωρολόγων λόγους), philosophical (13.8: φιλοσόφων λόγων λόγον) or poetic (9.1-2: λόγους ποίησιν ἅπασαν καὶ μέτρον λόγον λόγον μέτρον). Λόγος, or rather the sum of several λόγοι (15.2-3: τῶι τετάρτωι λόγωι), is the very work of Gorgia (3.2: ὅδε ὁ λόγος); it is either oral or written (13.7: γραφείς). In one case, Gorgia uses the term to indicate the concept of relation (14, cf. e.g. (213)): in the latter case, in which the term has a particular meaning, part of the tradition replaces it with νόμος.</comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0593.1st1K001.1st1K-grc1:16.5@νόμου:rdgs:"> . It is probable, in fact, that in this case the substitution is conjectural, and not introduced by slip of the tongue.</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0593.1st1K001.1st1K-grc1:21.1@τῷ-21.1@νόμῳ:rdgs:">The suppositus ζ, dependent on β, is identified by a group of five manuscripts. The double lesson suggests that a marginal variant, or s.l., was read in the ζ antigraph.</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:ARISTOTELES.en.VERSION:5.61134a30-1135b1@λόγον:rdgs:">Aristotle is dealing with justice and injustice within a political community, and their relationship with the νόμος: to avoid lʼἀδικεῖν (i.e. the bad distribution of goods and evils), we must not let one man rule, but the rational principle (λόγος). Marc. 213 (Mb) reports νόμον: the variant is favoured by Echoschreibung (it is present at ll. 30 and 31) and exchange of assonant bisyllables, but above all it generates a text acceptable also from the point of view of meaning. In this specific case, however, the two terms indicate two different and not overlapping concepts.</comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0004.tlg001.perseus-grc1:1.102.11@λόγον:rdgs:">); Long 1964; Marcovich 1999; Dorandi 2016.  Richards 1904, 345.</comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0019.tlg003.perseus-grc2:1198@παθεῖν:rdgs:"> . The verse is also handed down by Ath. Deipn. 171c and the corresponding passage Ath. Epit. 2.1 57, 14, in both cases with the lesson ποεῖν. ( Hermann 1830, 161-162. Cf. also Rogers 1950.  Starkie 1911, 260. See also Dover 1968, Sommerstein 1982.  Starkie 1911, 260.  )</comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0011.tlg003.perseus-grc2:647@φύει:rdgs:"> . The sentence needs a causative verb, with the meaning of ʻrendere, to make the φύει of tradition seem appropriate to the majority of publishers and the Herwerden conjecture was consequently rejected. The most common verb (but also the most banal) to indicate the work of time is ποιέω, which is found in the tradition of Stobeo (Stob. I 97.15). ( Kamerbeek 1953, I 135.  Campbell 1873 II; Jebb 1896; Lloyd Jones-Wilson 1990; Dawe 19963; Garvie 1998.  )</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0011.tlg003.perseus-grc2:1367@πονεῖν:rdgs:"> . The verb ποιεῖ is perhaps, according to Dawe, found in Par. gr. 2735 (C): according to this lesson, clearly trivialized, every man acts for himself. ( Weinstock 1936, 58.  Garvie 1998, 247.  Buhler 1982, IV 100.  Dawe 1973, 14 and 17.  )</comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0011.tlg005.perseus-grc2:947@τελεῖν:rdgs:">. However, he noted that theutrum in alterum is in favour of τελεῖν, which perhaps seemed to lack an object complement. Cambpbell added that the perfect emphatic βεβούλευμαι fits well with a verb of decisive action, such as τελεῖν. ( Hermann 1827 I; Campbell 1873 II; Kamerbeek 1974 V; Finglass 2007.  Campbell 1873 II.  Pearson 1948.  Dawe 19963.  )</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg005.perseus-grc1:387@πράγματα:rdgs:">Καιρὸς has, in the 5th century, various meanings, all related to the idea of ʻgiusto, proper, relevant. In this context, in particular, the term has a philosophical connotation: it is the sum of the characteristics that identify a body (Barrett 1964, 231.) . If the two types of αἰδώς, the positive and the negative, were certainly distinguishable, there would be two terms to define them; since this is not the case, one is forced to use the same word for both. The linguistic reference escaped a part of the tradition, in which we read the generic lesson πράγματα, which shifts discourse away from the field of language theories.</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0011.tlg003.perseus-grc2:1130@νόμους:rdgs:">The δαιμόνων γένος expression is quite frequent: it is found for example in Aesch. Sept. 236 (οὔτοι φθονῶ σοι δαιμόνων τιμᾶν γένος), Eur. fr. 557,2 Kn. (ἐγὼ μὲν εὖτʼ ἂν τοὺς κακοὺς ὁρῶ βροτῶν / πίπτοντας, εἶναι φημὶ δαιμόνων γένος.), Critias fr. 19,46 Sn.-Kn. (οὕτω δὲ δὲ πρῶτον οἴομαι τινα / θνητοὺς νομίζειν δαιμόνων εἶναι γένος ), Plut. De def. or. 416e 8-9 (οἱ τὸ τῶν δαιμόνων γένος ), but also in Christian production, for example in Clem. Al. Strom. VII 6 32 1.2 (πότερον διαπνεῖται ὡς τὸ τῶν δαιμόνων γένος;), Euseb. PE 15 7.3 Mras (τὸ τῶν μοχθηρῶν δαιμόνων γένος), Euseb. The fact that, in the substitution, the case is also modified suggests that this frequent expression has appeared, spontaneously and in an irreflexible way, to the mind of a copyist.</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0019.tlg003.perseus-grc2:954@φανήσεται:rdgs:">In this case, the two variants both indicate a future result: the replacement does not change the meaning of the text.</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0004.tlg001.perseus-grc1:1.1.1@ἔργον:rdgs:">The correct lesson is certainly ἔργον, handed down by Laur. 55, 1 (F) and from Par. gr. 1759 (P), two manuscripts among those that report in full the text of Diogenes Laertius . Τὸ τῆς φιλοσοφίας ἔργον indicates philosophy as a practice, as a discipline: the sentence concerns, in fact, the hypothesis that the barbarians practiced philosophy first. Cf. Gal. Plac. VIII 3 K. (τῆς θεωρητικῆς φιλοσοφίας ἔργον) and Plut. De Alex. fort. 328a 7 (τούτοις γὰρ ὁρίζουσι φιλοσοφίαν οἱ λόγον αὐτὴν οὐκ ἔργον νομίζοντες). The expression τὸ γένος, reported by Vat. gr. 96 (Φ), the so-called Excerpta Vaticana, indicates instead the type, the kind of something, like e.g. in Plut. Quomodo adul. 19 and 7-8 (παρὰ δʼ Ὁμήρῳ σιωπώμενόν ἐστι τὸ τοιοῦτο γένος τῆς διδασκαλίας) and in Ath. Deipn. XI 66 14 (ἀρχαικὸν ἦν ἦν τὸ τοιοῦτον [δὲ] τῆς ἀγωγῆς γένος). However, the sentence is completely intelligible and acceptable even with the erroneous variant: and ἔργον - if γένος were the only lesson to be learned - would hardly have been accepted as conjecture.</comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0004.tlg001.perseus-grc1:1.17.10@κατατρίβονται:rdgs:">Diogenes reviews the names of the main philosophical schools, briefly describing their etymology: the dialectics are characterized by ʻverbal juggleryʼ . Hicks and Marcovich prefer καταγίνονται : διαλεκτικοὶ are those who deal (cf. LSJ9) with ʻverbal juggleryʼ . Dorandi on the contrary chooses κατατρίβονται: between the Neap. III B 29 (B), Par. gr. 1759 (P) and Laur. 69, 13 (F), the three oldest continuous manuscripts, F is contaminated with the ʻvulgataʼ tradition of excerpta and, however useful, its use requires caution. The verb κατατρίβω, moreover, is used in the sense of ʻpassare time, using it completely (doing something)ʼ (Dem. Eubul. 9.1: κατέτριψε τὴν ἡμέραν δημηγορῶν, Xen. Mem. IV 7 5.7-8: ἔφη δὲ καὶ ἱκανὰ εἶναι κατατρίβειν ἀνθρώπου βίον), but also has in itself the sense of ʻconsumareʼ, ʻutilizzare wastingʼ (Ar. fr. 221.1 K.-A.: αὐλοῖς καὶ λύραισι κατατριμμαι χρώμενος): the verb could well describe the continuous and repetitive character of the action described as τὴν τῶν λόγων τερθρείαν.</comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0011.tlg003.perseus-grc2:864@ὕστατον:rdgs:">The phenomenon of the intruding glossa is, often, well recognizable by comparison with existing lexicons or clues scattered in the text:The two terms are often associated in lexicons: Cf. e.g. Hes. IV 221 846 (ὕστατα- ἔσχατα) and 847 (ὕστατον- ἐσχάτιον, τελευταῖον).</comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg002.perseus-grc2:0.2.23@Ἀπόλλων:rdgs:">The hypothesis in question is preserved by Vat. gr. 909 (V) and only partially by Par. gr. 2713 (P) and Laur. 31, 10 (O). After a brief summary of the plot, the text mostly provides erudite indications, such as information on the dating, the context of the tragic act and considerations (derived from Aristot. Po. 1453a) on the positive ending, which makes the drama closer to the comic genre (τὸ δὲ δρᾶμα κωμικωτέραν ἔχει τὴν καταστροφήν, l. 16; τὸ δὲ ἔχει ἐστι σατυρικώτερον, l. 21). Peculiar that V ʻde-personifies the god Apollo, writing that the prologue is pronounced by Helios. Perhaps, in this case, it was a glossa that was based on the identification between the two figures, perhaps born in an orphic-pitagoric environment, known to Aeschylus and Euripides and widely spread from Stoic doctrine onwards. (Buffière 1956, 187-200)</comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg002.perseus-grc2:0.2@Θάνατος:rdgs:">, Pal. gr. 287</comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:etc:schol_pynd:doesntexist:8.85.6@μόρου:rdgs:">The two nouns are synonymous because they share the translated meaning of ʻmorteʼ: one as an extension of ʻfine, completionʼ, the other from ʻdestino, fateʼ. However, lexicons and scolis never use one to gloss the other, while it happens that both are used as glossants (Suda τ 247, IV 517 A.: Τέκμωρ: τέλος, μόρον, θάνατον). It seems more likely that the metric and semantic equivalence of the two terms made them perfectly substitutable even in ancient variants.</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0011.tlg003.perseus-grc2:1000@δύστηνος:rdgs:">In Sophocles δύστηνος is present 61 times, while δείλαιος only fifteen (e.g. Ant. 1310-11: δείλαιος ἐγώ, αἰαῖ, / δειλαίᾳ δὲ συγκέκραμαι δύᾳ.). In addition, the first is found nine times in Ajax, where, on the contrary, the second is not certified. In itself, the numerical probability has no value, but the last data leads to the question: if δείλαιος was not introduced in the text for Echoschreibung - even from a distance - then how would the error be born? Lexicons do not attest to glossa in one sense or the other. The first adjective in this case is to be found in most of the tradition (HGR are representatives of the same family, while ADXrXsXz, from the Byzantine era, report a contaminated text, probably deriving from Moscopulo's edition) and seems clearly, both in Sophocles and in tragedy in general, a lectio facileor, a lexeme typical of self-pity on stage. The choice between the two adjectives, perhaps, is not as immediate as it seems in most editions: it is necessary to question the probability that a substitution like δύστηνος for δείλαιος is polygenetic. (Dawe 1973, 35. Hermann 1827 I chooses δείλαιος. On the contrary, δύστηνος is located in Jebb 1896; Campbell 1873 II; Lloyd Jones-Wilson 1990; Dawe 19963; Garvie 1998.</comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0011.tlg003.perseus-grc2:223@αἴθοπος:rdgs:">The two adjectives αἴθων and αἶθοψ have very similar meanings, connected to being ʻbruciante, incandescentʼ, both literally and figuratively, to indicate pride and value (Eur. Rhes. 122: αἴθων γὰρ ἁνὴρ καὶ πεπύργωται θράσει): a comparable case can be found in Hes. Op. 363 , where for αἴθοπα λιμόν Bergk designed αἴθονα, based on various parallels (Aesch. Sept. 448: αἴθων τέτακται λῆμα; Eur. Rhes. 122; Aeschin. 3.184: λιμόν τʼαἴθωνα, cf. Plut. Cim. 7; Callim. H. 6.67: λιμόν / αἴθωνα; schol. ad Lycophr. 1396 (II 385): ὁ δʼ Ἐρυσίχθων ἐκαλεῖτο, ὥς φησιν Ἡσίοδος διὰ τὸν λιμόν; Sud. α 133, II 165-166 A.: λιμόν αἴθων). (The presence of αἴθονος with ο instead of ω could be explained by the analogy of normal adjectives in -ων. The lecture αἴθοπος is accepted by Kamerbeek 1953 I; αἴθωνος, instead, by Jebb 1896; Campbell 1873 II; Lloyd Jones-Wilson 1990; Dawe 19963; Garvie 1998 (which traces a brief etymological picture). The publishers are mainly divided on the relevance of the suffix -οψ in this context: according to Jebb the adjective would refer only to ʽcomplectionʼ. According to Kamerbeek, instead, it would have lost its original meaning and the two lessons would be perfectly synonymic Cf. Kamerbeek 1953 I, 64-65. Bergk 1878-1882.</comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg015.perseus-grc2:11@μιᾶς-11@μητρὸς:rdgs:">The verse, excerpted for the first time in Paley's edition, defines - in a way considered redundant - the relationship between Creon and Jocasta. The variant ἐκ μιᾶς γαστρὸς conveys the same content. (Paley 1860. Mastronarde 2004, 144-145.).</comment>


			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg003.noedition:261@θυμουμένην:rdgs:">So Creon defines Medea. Only Vindob. gr. 17 (Nv) shows the participle μισουμένην. The two verbs θυμόω and μισέω, have a similar meaning, but not identical, so much so that in lexicons and scoliographic collections there are no cases in which one is used to gloss the other. More than a glossa, one can think of a synonymic, perhaps almost hyperonymic substitution: θυμόω is properly ʻodiare with angerʼ, while the copyist of Nv reports the most common verb to indicate hate.</comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0019.tlg006.perseus-grc2:1380@λιγύφθογγος:rdgs:">. The other publishers unanimously adopt λιγύφθογγος. ( Dunbar 1995, 668. )</comment>


			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0004.tlg001.perseus-grc1:1.8.84@μαγέιαν:rdgs:">Diogenes is describing the habits and customs of the barbarian peoples, with particular attention to the sapiential disciplines that could be compared to Greek philosophy. A few lines earlier, the author wrote about the Magi (I 7.3-4): ἀσκεῖν τε μαντικὴν καὶ πρόρρησιν, καὶ θεοὺς ἐμφανίζεσθαι λέγοντας. In the above mentioned passage, Diogenes reports that the Magi themselves would be completely inexperienced in magic: but Par. gr. 1759 (P) makes a substitution that, minimal from the paleographic point of view, gives back a rather coherent meaning in itself.</comment>


			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0004.tlg001.perseus-grc1:1.20.9-10@δόγμασιν:rdgs:">Skeptics cannot be considered a true philosophical school because they do not have a coherent and absolute doctrine: νόημα has the philosophical meaning of ʻconcettoʼ , but it is not suitable to define the principles that characterize a philosophical school. In this case the partial semantic affinity between the terms and the proximity of the verb νοοῖμεν (see below, § 3.4.1) have favoured error.</comment>


			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg006.perseus-grc2:425@χέρας:rdgs:">Menelaus orders the slaves to bring him Andromache, with their hands tied. The copyist of Par. gr. 2713 (B) writes however δέμας, a term that indicates the body as a whole: the meaning has been intensified but not radically changed, due to an exchange of axonant bisyllables.</comment>


			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0019.tlg003.perseus-grc2:3@ἀπέραντον:rdgs:">The night for Strepsiade is a difficult time: the old man canʼt sleep, tormented as he is by his sonʼs debts. On the adjective reported at χρῆμα τῶν νυκτῶν, the manuscripts do not agree: some report an adjective related to περαίνω (ʻterminare, put an endʼ), while others an adjective related to περάω (ʻattraversare, go beyondʼ). The two adjectives are so similar, and the error is so easily polygenetic, that the coat of arms does not help us. The metrics in this case are not resolutive either. But the meaning allows us to surely choose the version with the ν, despite the contrary opinion expressed in Suda (Sud. α 3035 (I 272 A.): Ἀπέρατον: ἄπειρον, μέγα, οὗ πέρας οὐκ ἔστιν. οἱ δὲ τοῦ ν γράφοντες ἁμαρτάνουσιν. Ἀριστοφάνης Νεφέλαις- τὸ χρῆμα τῶν ὅσον ἀπέρατον. καὶ αὖθις αὖθις- ὁ δὲ Χοσρόης ἀπέραντον καλουμένην εἰρήνην λαμπρῶς παρέλυσεν. ) ἀπέρατος in classical Greek is used for something that should not be crossed (Aesch. Suppl. 1049-50: Διὸς οὐ παρβατός ἐστιν / μεγάλα φρὴν ἀπέρατος), while ἀπέρατος applies for example to weather (Plat. Polit. 302a: χρόνον ἀπέραντον) and air (Ar. Nub. 393: τὸν δʼ ἀέρα τόνδʼ ὄντʼ ἀπέραντον). However, the position recorded in Suda and the frequent oscillation in the manuscripts suggests that the two adjectives became, at a certain point in their use, almost synonymous.</comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0019.tlg003.perseus-grc2:649@κομψὸν:rdgs:">Κομψός is said to be a person of subtle and profound intellect. The epithet is used by Aristophanes both ironically (cf. Vesp. 1317: ἐπὶ τῷ κομᾷς καὶ κομψὸς εἶναι προσποιεῖ,) and honestly admired (cf. Av. 195: μὴ ʻγὼ νόημα κομψότερον ἤκουσά πω). The Marc. 474 (V) replaces it with an assonant synonym with a more generic meaning: it cannot, however, be excluded that the variant derives from a glossa.</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0004.tlg001.perseus-grc1:1.70.9@ἐχθαίρειν:rdgs:">These precepts are part of a long list of maxims attributed to Hippocrates. The Neap copyist. III B 29 (B) modifies the sense of one of them that, from favorable towards the oracular practice, is changed into deeply adverse.</comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0019.tlg003.perseus-grc2:215@μεταφροντίζετε:rdgs:">. Probably, however, πάνυ was generated by μέγα (by synonymy, by glossa intrusion or by the influence of v. 216), which remains only in Suda (μ 348, III 341 A.: Μέγα: ἀντὶ τοῦ μεγάλως. Ἀριστοφάνης Νεφέλαις- τοῦτο μέγα φροντίζετε.). Bentley hypothesized, however, that a scolium at v. 215 was a trace of an ancient lesson μεταφροντίζετε, an aristophanesque coinage with the meaning of ʻcambiate idea, think againʼ. If this were so, discretion and a trivial paleographic exchange (τ / γ) would have created a trivialising version with almost the opposite meaning: in the case of μέγα μεταφροντίζετε, in fact, τοῦτο would refer to the mission to move Sparta, made explicit in the next verse, to which the disciples should devote body and soul according to Strepsiade; in the case of μεταφροντίζετε , instead, τοῦτο would stand for ʻla decision to put Sparta near Athensʼ, i.e. the previous verse.</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg033.perseus-grc2:6.91@ἀγαφθέγκτων:rdgs:">In this way Pindar defines Aineas, the coryphaean: but in Ambr. C 222 inf. (A) the ʻdolce craterʼ is filled with songs ʻprivi of voiceʼ. This could be an example of a real polar error: the meaning changes radically and with a meaningless outcome. However, it should be noted that the palaeographic similarity is not absent: indeed ἀφθόγγων is almost perfectly ʻcontenutoʼ in the letters that compose ἀγαφθέγκτων.</comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0011.tlg003.perseus-grc2:224@φευκτάν:rdgs:">Tecmessa just announced that Ajax has been struck by madness. The oxymoronic contrast of the unbearable message that cannot be escaped is eliminated by Heid. Pal. gr. 40 (P): ἄτλατον οὐδὲ suggests in fact a synonymic dictology, favored by the great palaeographic similarity.</comment>


			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg3068.tlg005.noedition:9P8@ἐρυθρὸν:rdgs:">Carme is an invocation to the mania provoked by wine, legitimated by examples of illustrious Greeks who have committed follies: but the wine the poet drinks becomes white in a marginal note of Par. Suppl. gr. 384 (P). We can be sure that the wine mentioned in this passage was red and not white, and not only for a matter of conformity to the topoi of Greek literature (the white wine, judged by Ateneo ἀσθενὴς καὶ λεπτός , seems unsuitable for this kind of Dionysian drunkenness): at v. 5 we find in fact χὠ λευκόπους Ὀρέστης. The recurrence at short distance of the two antonyms to indicate the colors of the wine and has modified the drink in the cups, generating a consistent variant that tradition has brought up to us. In this case, the Echoschreibung generated a co-hyponymic variation, with the replacement of two terms indicating one colour (and, specifically, the two specialised as attributes of the wine).</comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg3068.tlg005.noedition:2311@ἥρωες:rdgs:">The poet would like to sing the deeds of the Atrides, of Cadmus, of Heracles, but his lyre persists in producing love compositions. Let the heroes resign themselves: Anacreon says goodbye to them. The final line was restored by Henri Estienne, the first editor of the text: in Par. Suppl. gr. 384 (P) we read έρωτεσ. An error clearly dictated by the presence of the terms ἔρωτα (v. 4) and ἔρωτας (vv. 9 and 12), but also by the meaning of the sentence and, perhaps, by an incorrect interpretation of v. 10, according to which the poet would exhort loves to rejoice, because they will be the protagonists of his songs.</comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0011.tlg005.perseus-grc2:1205@ἄγγος:rdgs:">A stranger has brought back to Electra the day containing Orestesʼ ashes: as a condition for revealing his identity to her, however, the stranger insists for a long time (see 1171-1231) that she leave the alleged remains of her brother. According to the text of the Laur. Conv. suppr. 152 (G) and Vat. gr. 2291 (R), Orestes insists with his sister that she ʻdeponga the painʼ. The error has certainly suffered, from a formal point of view, the influence of v. 1201 (μόνος γὰρ ἥκω τοῖσι σοῖς ἀλγῶν κακοῖς): but, in the erroneous version, Orestesʼ request is not senseless from a thematic point of view, since he is about to reveal to Electra that his pain has no reason to exist: in a certain sense, the slip - to use a term from Havet - is unʼʻanticipazioneʼ, but of an ideological character.</comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg012.perseus-grc2:311@γυναῖκας:rdgs:"> . Again, a term was not repeated by pure mnemonic echo: it was inserted into the text in a manner consistent with the verse he insisted on and also with the previous statements of Electra. A defence of the intervention in Kovacs 1985, 306-310. Against, instead, cf. Seaford 1996, 319 no. 38. Cropp 1988, 120.</comment>


			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0011.tlg004.perseus-grc2:942@ἐν-942@τάφοις:rdgs:">Dawe's comment to the step is noteworthy: the variant for τάφοις is stylistically superior, and it is easy to see how τάφοις could have started life as a gloss. But it is none too well attested, and the messenger might be no great stylist, to the question ʻIsnʼt Polybus still in power?ʼ blunting replying: ʻNo; he is dead and buriedʼ . In other words, the utrum in alterum would be in favour of δόμοις because of the funereal topic of the verse, which could well be accompanied by a glossa concerning the tomb of Polybus. The variant discussed, however, is preceded by the word θάνατος: if a corruptelae ratio should be invoked, it is not that of the intruding glossa, but - in all probability - that of a common slip calami born from the influence of the previous word. Dawe's comment is emblematic of the lack of consideration given to psycholinguistic error, and of the search for the mechanical cause as a guarantee of plausibility of conjecture.</comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0011.tlg005.perseus-grc2:1460@πάρος:rdgs:">Egistus has been deceived with the false news of Orestes' death: addressing the citizens of Mycenae and Argos, he invites them to acknowledge that past empty hopes are now useless. The model of Laur. Conv. Soppr. 152 (G) and Vat. gr. 2291 (R) writes μάτην at the end of the verse, replacing adverb to adverb and emphasizing the vanity of the hopes mentioned by Egistus. According to Finglass this would be an attempt to improve the text by inserting a more incisive word: but the adverb, redundant in itself, seems instead the result of an interpretative copying, which maintains the syntactic function of the term to be copied but adjusts its meaning to the words immediately preceding it.</comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg003.noedition:329@πολύ:rdgs:">: the verse would thus repeat, in fact, the content of Creon's previous line (v. 327). There is no need to think of a voluntary intervention: it is possible that the variant is born in an irreflexible way due to the influence of the previous verses. Again, even if with different conclusions, the hypothesis of the slip is not taken into consideration: the sensible nature ʻsemanticamente of the exchange is necessarily traced back to a voluntary intervention.</comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0011.tlg004.perseus-grc2:1322@ἐμὸς-1322@ἐπίπολος:rdgs:">The choir has just discovered Jocasta's suicide and the resulting blinding of Oedipus. The protagonist, back on stage, turns to the choir, commenting in amazement on the constant presence at its side, even in such harrowing circumstances. The word ἐπίπολος is, as far as we know, a sofocleo coinage modeled on πρόσπολος and πρόσπολος , to indicate the idea of a person who remains at someoneʼs side. A scolio al Laur. 32, 9 (schol. ad Soph. OT 1322, I 209 Xenis) reports: γράφεται καὶ ἐμοῖς ἐπὶ πόνοις. The variant intervenes on an extremely rare term with minimal (if metrically incorrect) palaeographic modification. It is probably not a case of Echoschreibung: the term πόνος does not appear anywhere near v. 1322. The error must have been inspired in the copyist by the generic theme of pain, which has been continuously repeated in previous verses (ἐν τοσοῖσδε πήμασιν v. 1319, πενθεῖν, θροεῖν κακά v. 1320).</comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0011.tlg005.perseus-grc2:427@τάφου:rdgs:">With these words Chrysotemi concludes the speech with which she relates to Elettra that Clitemestra had ordered her, through a dream harbinger of bad omens (ἐκ δείματός του νυκτέρου, δοκεῖν ἐμοί, v. 410) to place offerings on the tomb of her father (μήτηρ με πέμπει πατρὶ τυμβεῦσαι χοάς, v. 406). If the copyist of Ien. Bos. q. 7 (J) makes a mistake that can be easily explained (a repetition of a very similar hemistyle, τοῦδε τοῦ τάρβους πέρι, v. 412), it is the copyist of Matr. 4677 (N) who makes a more remarkable inattention. It should be noted that the word τάφος is present, in the Epistle, only twice, at vv. 1218-1219 (ΗΛ. ποῦ δʼ ἔστʼ τάφος ταλαιπώρου τάφος; / ΟΡ. οὐκ ἔστι- τοῦ γὰρ ζῶντος οὐκ ἔστιν τάφος). It is not, therefore, a question of lexical influence: the meaning of v. 410 could, however, still be present in the mind of the copyist, who modifies the syntagma of v. 427 to obtain a uniformity of meaning between the motivations given by Chrysotemi at the beginning of the speech and those given at the end.</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg003.noedition:374@νεκρούς:rdgs:">These words are pronounced by Medea immediately after Creon announced her exile from Corinth the following day. The woman promises to take revenge against Creon, her daughter and Jason himself. Already on v. 278, having heard the will of Creon, the woman had declared: ἐχθροὶ γὰρ ἐξιᾶσι πάντα δὴ κάλων; now she reiterates the fact that her husband, the king who had welcomed her to Corinth and his daughter are, for her, adversaries to kill. Two manuscripts, Par. gr. 2712 (A) and the Laur. 31,15 (D), omit the word ἐχθρῶν. D also adds ἐγώ at the end of the verse, a clue perhaps that he tried to fill a gap in his own model. It is not difficult to hypothesize a mechanical error for such omission: the previous word, ἐμῶν, begins and ends with the same letters. However, it should be noted that the locution οἱ ἐμοί οἱ, in its various declensions, is found twelve times in Euripides; of these, seven attestations are needed in the Medea: the apparatus never records the loss of the noun except in this case. It is therefore possible that the error was also generated by the influence of the next verse, which enumerates three terms of kinship. (On the model of D for vv. 1-700 there is no certainty: for this section, the manuscript has a common ancestor with Athos, Μονὴ Ἰβήρων 209 (E), but that this is not a direct ancestor is proved by many lessons in which D agrees with other manuscripts (especially A) against E. Cf. Diggle 1983, 343-345).</comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0019.tlg003.perseus-grc2:1117@ἀγρούς:rdgs:">The Clouds that make up the choir promise the judges a favorable treatment, in case of a favorable judgment: among the various privileges offered, there is that of making it rain on their fields first. But the verb ὕσομεν immediately following and the anticipatory thought of the fields swollen with rain transformed τοὺς ἀγρούς into τοὺς ὑγρούς in the mind of the copyist of Rav. 429 (R), who noticed the slip and ran it. Contemporary corrections to the copy act are, for us, a precious source to really understand which mistakes are plausible and how much the psycholinguistic ratio influences them.</comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0019.tlg006.perseus-grc2:495@δειπνεῖν:rdgs:">Pisetero tells Evelpides about when, in town for a banquet, he had drunk some wine and fell asleep before the feast; awakened by the crowing of a rooster, he thought it was dawn and left. In reality, the banquet had not yet taken place and, because of a hasty rooster, Pisetero lost it. The verb ὑπέπινον must have suggested to the Amberʼs model. L 39 sup. (M) and Par. gr. 2712 (A) to replace, in the next verse, the action of the banquet with that of drinking: δὲ πίνειν was generated with the only movement of the ι and with a different divisio verborum. The variant δὲ πιεῖν seems, finally, generated to heal the ametric nature of the MA lesson.</comment>


			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0011.tlg003.perseus-grc2:367@ἄρα:rdgs:">Ajax laments his wretched fate, comparing it to the glories of yesteryear. The variant overwritten in the Laur. 28, 25 (F) is a modification so to speak ʻintensivaʼ and pathetic, because it inserts in the passage a final adjective linked to the self-pity of the protagonist, intensifying the meaning of the verse in a way consistent with the previous sentences.</comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0019.tlg003.perseus-grc2:384@πυκνότητα:rdgs:">Socrates illustrates to Strepsiade his theory on the genesis of thunder: the clouds, heavy with rain, strike each other producing thunder. The cause of this phenomenon is, according to all the manuscripts, their density (πυκνότης). The Marc alone. 474 (V) attributes it to their being full of water (ὑγρότης). A repetition of ὕδατος μεστὰς in the previous verse, which probably arose due to the influence of the latter, and rather indifferent to purely mechanical reasons.</comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg003.noedition:503@πάτραν:rdgs:">Medea bitterly notes that she does not know where to go if she is expelled from Corinth: she certainly cannot return to her native house, which she betrayed for Jason along with her homeland. The error of Vat. gr. 910 (Vc) probably derives from the association of ideas between her fatherʼs house and her first house.</comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg002.perseus-grc2:1089@λέχος:rdgs:">LPQ's χηρεύεις μόνος clearly will not do: we need a future, not a present, and μόνος is absurdly redundant' (Parker 2007, 268.) . The variant originates from ʻcotestualeʼ: the second half of the verse, partially lost in the memory of a copyist, was replaced with material that reiterated and specified οὐ γαμεῖς.</comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg033.perseus-grc2:2.22@εὐθρόνοις:rdgs:">P. Oxy's copyist. 17.2092 (Π2), reading ἕπεται δὲ λόγος εὐ-, did not notice the word that separated εὐθρόνοις from the related noun (κούραις); instead, he believed that the word beginning for εὐ- was an adjective related to λόγος, making the structure of the sentence more prosaic and partially changing its meaning.</comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg001.noedition:510@ἔνδος-510@μοι:rdgs:">In the verses quoted, the Cyclops invites you to give him the otre (ἀσκὸν ἔνδος μοι). Par. gr. 2712 (A), however, perhaps thinking of ἔνδον, moved only one letter, the ς, and derived from the anagram ʻhousmanianoʼ (cf. § 2.4) a place complement.</comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg3068.tlg005.noedition:18.4@προδοθεὶς:rdgs:">The poet asks for a glass of wine, because he is exhausted from the heat. The variant πυρωθείς must have come about through the influence of the agent complement (ἀπὸ καύματος).</comment>


			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0019.tlg003.perseus-grc2:1176@τἀττικὸν:rdgs:">Pheidippides has, according to his father, an innocent and unsuspected air just as he prepares to commit injustices: the typical aspect of the Athenian. In fact, however, the description of the young man is that of someone who is putting a fraudulent plan into practice; and τακτικὸν is, in fact, the βλέπος according to a variant: an adjective derived with a minimal change from τἀττικὸν, but from the meaning in its own way appropriate to the context.</comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg017.perseus-grc2:451@μέθεσθε:rdgs:">Μέθεσθε is a unanimously accepted correction (Murray 1913; Dodds 1960; Seaford 1996, 59 etc.) : the lesson handed down by Laur. 32, 2 (L) and Vat. Pal. gr. 287 (P) is μαίνεσθε: in the previous verses the guards had reported to Pentheus about the miraculous escape of the Bacchae. In this case, tradition has inserted a verb profoundly suitable for tragedy tout court, but inappropriate for the passage itself: the influence of the general context has prevailed over that exerted by the immediate context.</comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg003.noedition:400@κῆδος:rdgs:">. the Ath. Iber. 209 (olim 161) (W) and the Laur. 31, 15 (D) agree with Nv in some errors (e.g. see 411: δίκαια for δίκα; see 604: φευξοῦμαι for φευξοῦμαι; see 607: τύρανννος for τυράννοις). The two manuscripts, although linked by 'certain proximitas . diverge on this lesson: it is perhaps possible that precisely W is, at this point, a model of Nv, of which some peculiarities have already been highlighted (cf. § 3.3.1). (Van Looy 1992, XXI, Van Looy 1992, XVIII.).</comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg003.noedition:594@γῆμαί:rdgs:">The second episode of the Medea is entirely occupied by the quarrel between the protagonist and Jason, who tries to defend his choice to marry Glauce and to appease the anger of his betrayed companion: the purpose of his new union would be mainly to protect the children of first bed, giving them native and royal blood brothers who legitimize their status; Jason specifies, on the other hand, that the choice qualifies him as a wise man and immune to passions (vv. 547-550) and is not dictated by annoyance towards the bed of Medea or by lust for a new bride (vv. 555-556). The verses reported are the last, desperate attempt to reiterate one's reasons for the contemptuous treatment of the woman. A papyrus dated to the 1st century B.C. (Pap. Heid. G 1385) reports the lesson τλῆναι με λέκτρα. Tedeschi alone, in an article of 1986 (Tedeschi 1986), defended her: with this lesson, the verse would allude to the Homeric passage in which Tethys confesses to having been forced to join Pelaeus (Il. XVIII 433-434: καὶ ἔτλην ἀνέρος εὐνὴν / πολλὰ μάλʼ οὐκ ἐθέλουσα); the verse would also be consistent with Jason's attempt to show that his feelings are still for Medea; the manuscripts' lesson would finally be a trivialization based on a typically Euripidan expression (Ion. 297: γαμεῖ λέχος; Tro. 44: γαμεῖ βιαίως σκότιον Ἀγαμέμνων λέχος. Hel. 784: ἦ γὰρ γαμεῖν τις τἄμʼ λέχη; El. 936: γήμαντι καὶ μείζω λέχη). However, at this point Jason is reporting, to deny it, the opinion of Medea: it is she who believes that he wants to join Glauce γυναικὸς οὕνεκα: at the end of the long and heated dialogue, Jason would like to reiterate at least the falsity of this recrimination. The accusation canʼt be to bear the new bride, but to join her more than willingly: it would not make sense, therefore, to attribute to Medea a verb like τλῆναι. Probably, the variant was born by general influence of Jasonʼs tones and justifications, but the misogynistic slip cannot be excluded.</comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0011.tlg004.perseus-grc2:870-871@λάθα:rdgs:">We find ourselves in the first verses of the second stasis, in which the chorus is poured out in expressions of praise for pure words and actions, which are like laws that descend directly from the Olympus and are not generated by mortals. With the variant to vv. 870-871, the sentence changes radically its meaning: the subject, i.e. the oblivion, which is hoped never to put divine laws to rest, fails in favour of the adverb meaning ʻdi hidden, secretlyʼ. It is therefore assumed that the verb κατακοιμάσῃ is, in the erroneous structure of the sentence, referred to the last known subject: human nature (θνατὰ φύσις) of v. 869. The new meaning would be, therefore: the divine laws have as their only father the Olimpus; the mortal nature of men has not generated them and it is hoped that it will not put them to rest in secret. The erroneous version replaces a consideration of the eternity of divine laws with what may seem a hint of future developments in the plot: the copyist who has been in error has perhaps unconsciously expressed his thoughts on the plot of the tragedy that the passage has aroused in him.</comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg002.perseus-grc2:665@θάψω:rdgs:">Admeto reproaches his father for his decision not to sacrifice himself for him, but to let Alcesti die. The son announces, moreover, his own revenge: he won't put his hand at the funeral of the parent, when the time comes. The copyist of Vat. gr. 909 (V), however, with the addition of a single letter, transforms the meaning of the sentence: instead of not burying him, Admeto would threaten not to warm him up himself. Perhaps a reminiscence of the resurrection that the father denied his son? Or, simply, a lexical approach to the styles of funeral lament, pertinent to the theme of the death of the parent?</comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:etc:tyrt:doesntexist:10.29@ἐρατῆς:rdgs:">The vocal anagram inserts a term that does not fit with the syntax in which it is inserted, but whose meaning makes its genesis evident by association of ideas with the surrounding verses and, in general, with Tyrrhenian production.</comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0019.tlg006.perseus-grc2:121@εὔερον:rdgs:"> Dunbar 1995, 53.) in fact, ἀέριον, while the Vat. Urb. 141 (U) defines the city εὐάερον. The same variant is found in the margin of Par. gr. 2715 (B).</comment>


			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg012.perseus-grc2:435@φί̆λαυλος:rdgs:">The chorus of the Elettra defines the dolphin ʻfond of the aulosʼ: we are able to reconstruct it thanks to the Euripidea parody in Aristophanesʼ Frogs (Ar. Ran. 1317-1319: ἵνʼ ὁ φίλαυλος ἔπαλλε δελ- / φὶς πρῴραις κυανεμβόλοις / μαντεῖα καὶ σταδίους). Perhaps the lesson handed down from the Euripid manuscript tradition arose from the influence of the general context, in a tragedy in which the theme of the alliance and affection between brothers is central.</comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg003.noedition:290@γύναι:rdgs:">The votive at the end of the verse is free from syntax and, as such, subject to corruption. The Ath. Vat. 36 (gV) in fact attempts to insert a bisyllable that is somehow pertinent to the syntax of the verse, which probably seemed to him suspended. Plutarch, on the other hand, introduces an appellative appropriate to the character of Medea, the foreigner par excellence, and which, however, has no relevance in the rest of the Euripidesque text. The verses are referred, by the author of Cheronea, to the attitude to be held towards unwelcome invitations, especially by people of rank or foreign guests (ἡγεμόνων καλούντων ἢ ξένων ἐπιφανέντων ): one may wonder, therefore, if Plutarch already read v. 290 in that form, if it is a slip of the author or if the plutarchea tradition has been influenced by the sentence preceding the quotation.</comment>


			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0008.tlg001.perseus-grc3:I.27.9@ἐναντίοι:rdgs:">There are various types of dances: some more frenetic, others involving the use of the ball, others even more harmonious and calm, as in some scenes from Homeric poems. The Laurʼs copyist. 60, 2 (E), one of the witnesses of the epitome of the Deipnosophists, perhaps unconsciously associated the dance with scenes of Dionysian matrix, writing ἐν μανία.</comment>


			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0019.tlg003.perseus-grc2:1496@οἰκίας:rdgs:">Strepsiade, just before setting fire to the Think Tank, makes fun of sophisticated logic. The verb διαλεπτολογοῦμαι is an aristophanesque coinage, which unites διαλέγομαι and λεπτολογέω: cf. 319-320: Στ. ταῦτʼ ἄρʼ ἀκούσασʼ ἀκούσασʼ αὐτῶν τὸ φθέγμʼ ἡ ψυχή μου πεπότηται / καὶ λεπτολογεῖν ἤδη ζητεῖ καὶ περὶ καπνοῦ στενολεσχεῖν. The copyist of V, at the end of v. 1496, writes αἰτίας (but the correct lesson is reported in the margin of the code): perhaps a slip of the tongue, due to the parodic use of terms related to logic and Socratic disquisitions.</comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg006.perseus-grc2:360@ἀπαιδίαν:rdgs:">Andromache, taken prisoner after the capture of Troy, is assigned to Neottolemus, with whom she has a son; but Hermione, daughter of Menelaus and lawful wife of Neottolemus, accuses her of making her barren. In a verbal confrontation with Menelaus, father of Hermione, the Trojan woman states that she is ready to stand trial and, if found guilty, to be punished (βλάβην ὀφείλω) for Hermione's infertility. Part of the tradition replaces infertility with lʼἀβουλία, i.e. lack of judgment, superficiality in making decisions. Is this, perhaps, a variant born from the influence of the rest of Andromacheʼs discourse? Lʼἀβουλία refers to his hypothetical bad behavior, in causing the infertility of ʻrivaleʼ? One may also wonder whether ἀπαιδίαν, in the absence of attestations, would be considered an acceptable conjecture. Murray finally points out the conjecture ἀκυμίαν (a term not attested but connected with the verb κύω), attributed to Headlam, which evidently presupposed a double paleographic error starting from ἀβουλίαν, and - perhaps - the insertion of the glossa ἀπαιδίαν.</comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0019.tlg003.perseus-grc2:417@οἴνου:rdgs:">Among the behavioral requirements to be a wise man, the Cloud Choir also indicates the need to be restrained by frivolousness. The characteristics indicated clearly target, on the one hand, the portraits of an abstinent and tireless Socrates, on the other hand, some key elements of Athenian life, such as the gymnasiums, dismissed as ἀνόητα. The manuscripts East. α. U.5.10 (III D 8) (E) and Ambr. L 39 sup. (M), both of XIV century, report a different lesson: the essay should not abstain from wine, but from sleep. The two manuscripts have very close editors, if we do not consider the corrections made on E with the help of a witness belonging to another branch of the tradition. In this case, the variant of the model of Eac and M is ancient: it dates back at least to the fifth century AD, because it is also reported by the Ethymologicon of Orion.</comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0011.tlg004.perseus-grc2:1025@τυχών:rdgs:">τυχών: all manuscripts have τεκών, which will hardly do after both sides have expressly said that the messenger is as unrelated to Oedipus as any one could possibly be. We seem to see before us the original Freudian scribal error. (Dave 20062, 161. Condello 2013, 59-74. Bothe 1826, 83: «scribendum puto ἢ τυχών, ut 986, vel ἢ ᾿ντυχών»</comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0020.tlg001.perseus-grc2:177@ἱμείρων:rdgs:">The variants are restricted to the r family, and seem to be independent of each other. Neither has an obvious explanation; possibly the scribe who wrote ἱμείρω, seeing the words ʻlonging for sexʼ, at once thought of his own longing (West 1973, 108-109.)</comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg033.perseus-grc2:9.14@ἐλελίζων:rdgs:">perhaps thinking of eels for lunch (Young 1965, 269)</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:etc:thgn:doesntexist:859@παυράκι:rdgs:">A polar error influenced by unconscious ʻwishful thinkingʼ?</comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0085.tlg002.perseus-grc2:240@πηγή:rdgs:">Laur.86, 3 (B)</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg016.perseus-grc2:1093@καλόν:rdgs:">The influence of co-text is, however, relevant in this case.</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:latinLit:phi1103.phi001.lascivaroma-lat1:72.2@minare:rdgs:">Boccaccio is the copyist</comment>


			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0027.tlg001.noedition:71@Ἰσοτιμίδης:rdgs:">Reiske 1771 understood that the copyist of the archetype had made a mistake due to the itacistic pronunciation of Greek, for which Ἰσοτιμίδης, οὗ and εἰς ὅτι μηδʼἴσου are articulated with the same vocal sounds. This error ʻuditivoʼ, together with the fact that the name Isotimide must have been unknown to the person responsible for the error, had led to an incorrect but, in its own way, remarkable solution.</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0008.tlg001.perseus-grc3:I 54.10@πρίηπος:rdgs:">And at first he writes Πρίαμος, then he corrects the μ in a π. It is not necessary to think that E has made a conceptual error, really confusing the god with the mythical Trojan king; the subsequent correction confirms the momentary nature of the slip. On the other hand, this error cannot even be reduced to a graphic oversight, since the substitution of a proper name with an existing name presupposes not only a wrong transcription, but a real error of selection within the semantic field of individual names.</comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0008.tlg001.perseus-grc3:I.4.21@Πομπιλίου:rdgs:">The error is quite similar to the previous one, but it must have been committed at a stage of tradition higher than C and E, both of which write to I 4.16 Ῥωμύλου καὶ Πομπηίου Νουμᾶ. Obviously, the correct diction, restored in the Aldina edited by Musuro in 1514 and in the 1597 edition of Casaubon, is Πομπιλίου: the next copyist or ephitomator would have made an error of choice in the category of Latin initials for Pomp-. Such an error, even if it had been made by the eptomator, would not help to corroborate Peppink's thesis about his ignorance of Latin: it probably has nothing to do with the writer's competence in the matter. What is noteworthy, however, is that an error so evident to us has survived in both C and E: this fact could be attributable to a type of mechanical copying, to uncritical fidelity to the model or (but seems unlikely) to actual ignorance of the name of the second king of Rome. Given the lack of accuracy that Kaibel complains about both witnesses, the most likely hypothesis is that they paid little attention to the content they were copying, uncritically transcribing its content. If this is the case, this passage must be a clue to the type of copying carried out by the copyists of E and C and, therefore, to the errors that can be attributed to them.</comment>


			<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0008.tlg001.perseus-grc3:I.5.34@ἐκ-I.5.34@Γέλας:rdgs:"> if linked to an object complement referring precisely to horses . The incomprehensible step, therefore, has been unconsciously smoothed out with the introduction of words that would adapt not only to the spelling, but also to the sense.</comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:latinLit:phi1103.phi001.lascivaroma-lat1:1.5@aequo:rdgs:">"Membriosior aequo", endowed with an unusually large penis, or "larger than that of a horse"? </comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:latinLit:phi1103.phi001.lascivaroma-lat1:2.5@virgineum:rdgs:">The place where the poem is sung would be unsuited for the Muses, being "so not virginal". It is clear how the place is denoted. It is not suited for the Muses. Some copyists write that is is "not innocent", but another reading is antinomic: the place is not "inguineum", not suited for sexual content. So the whole expression has been antinomically interpreted. The muses, in this interpretation, have been called.</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:latinLit:phi1103.phi001.lascivaroma-lat1:3.1@obscure:rdgs:">The verses 1-7 are an ironic riddle with a supposedly hidden sexual content that is made explicit in the last two verses. But a manuscript coherently reveals the obscene content by changing the first adverb.</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:latinLit:phi1103.phi001.lascivaroma-lat1:3.3@frustra:rdgs:">The riddle in the poem contains the topos of the unsuitedness of the erastos for homosexual intercourse after the beard sprout. So he will "in vain" (frustra) desire the poet when it is too late. The copyist of K, though, writes that the boy will maybe desire his own brother (?)</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:latinLit:phi1103.phi001.lascivaroma-lat1:4.4@pictas:rdgs:">The variant "pietas" for "pictas" is an example of the quite rare change of function. The syntax of the sentence is modified by the insertion of a nominative. Lalage, an unsatisfied woman, begs the god to help her put into action the erotic pictures that she offers to him. Here the subject of the "opus edere" is no more the god, but the woman's pietas. The reading well suits the ironic tone of the poem, since the woman is actually making a religious sacrifice, though a quite unpious one.</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:latinLit:phi1103.phi001.lascivaroma-lat1:12.1@iunior:rdgs:">The described woman is said to be "younger" than Hecuba, with a litotes that implies that she is indeed very old. The adjective must have been perceived as contradictory in its literal meaning, and thus it has been reverted in senior, non iunior, non minor. In the same direction goes the conjecture (?) canior.</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:latinLit:phi1103.phi001.lascivaroma-lat1:12.9@excreauit:rdgs:">The woman is so old and shabby that she "coughed off one of her three teeth during morning prayers". Many readings are recorded. In the reading "de tribus hec creavit unum", can the verb creo be suggested by the generically christian allure of the expression "de tribus unum"? </comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:latinLit:phi1103.phi001.lascivaroma-lat1:14.1@in-14.1@dei:rdgs:">The temple of the lascivious god becomes that of lhe lascivious jew. Why?</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:latinLit:phi1103.phi001.lascivaroma-lat1:16.7@puer:rdgs:">Both readings, pius and puer, have been chosen in different editions. Pius dominus is, though, an expression that can be found elsewere and that would be more likely to intrude as a slip of the pen.</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:latinLit:phi1103.phi001.lascivaroma-lat1:17.3@redibit:rdgs:">The anagram introduces a totally different meaning. The Priapic statue warns the robbers about the sexual violence that expects them if they trespass their guarded territories. There is a variant that implies that the robber, after the penetration, will laugh.</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:latinLit:phi1103.phi001.lascivaroma-lat1:24.3@poenam:rdgs:">The robber will have his punishment - but the punishment, by now it is clear, is always of a sexual kind.So, coherently, a variant changes "poenam", punishment, with "penem", penis.</comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:latinLit:phi1103.phi001.lascivaroma-lat1:27.6@exemplum:rdgs:">ad exemplum dei (as the god does) is changed into "at the god's temple. A cotextual slip.</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:latinLit:phi1103.phi001.lascivaroma-lat1:36.4@paeto:rdgs:">To every god of the Pantheon a feature is associated. Venus has what remained proverbial to these days, the "strabismus". But part of the tradition thinks of her chest.</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:latinLit:phi1103.phi001.lascivaroma-lat1:37.2@procreamur:rdgs:">Another interference between the semantic field of "sex" and that of "religion, prayer".</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:latinLit:phi1103.phi001.lascivaroma-lat1:40.2@puto:rdgs:">The manuscript T inserts an apposition that could not be more appropriate. Telethusa is, indeed, a prostitute. </comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:latinLit:phi1103.phi001.lascivaroma-lat1:40.2@suo:rdgs:">Another insertion of the religious theme. Telethusa would be made goddess (?)</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:latinLit:phi1103.phi001.lascivaroma-lat1:42.1@laetus:rdgs:"></comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:latinLit:phi1103.phi001.lascivaroma-lat1:43.1@velle:rdgs:">x</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:latinLit:phi1103.phi001.lascivaroma-lat1:43.2@mihi:rdgs:">x</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:latinLit:phi1103.phi001.lascivaroma-lat1:43.4@usibus:rdgs:">x</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:latinLit:phi1103.phi001.lascivaroma-lat1:43.4@rudis:rdgs:">x</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:latinLit:phi1103.phi001.lascivaroma-lat1:45.4@heus:rdgs:">x</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:latinLit:phi1103.phi001.lascivaroma-lat1:46@rivedi:rdgs:">x</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:latinLit:phi1103.phi001.lascivaroma-lat1:50.2@focosissima:rdgs:">x</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:latinLit:phi1103.phi001.lascivaroma-lat1:50.5@fruenda:rdgs:">x</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:latinLit:phi1103.phi001.lascivaroma-lat1:51@rivedi:rdgs:">x</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:latinLit:phi1103.phi001.lascivaroma-lat1:52.10@mutuniatus:rdgs:">x</comment>

			<comment ref="urn:cts:latinLit:phi1103.phi001.lascivaroma-lat1:55.2@digitis:rdgs:">x</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:latinLit:phi1103.phi001.lascivaroma-lat1:57.2@putida:rdgs:">x</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:latinLit:phi1103.phi001.lascivaroma-lat1:63.2@per caniculam:rdgs:">x</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:latinLit:phi1103.phi001.lascivaroma-lat1:63.18@pruriosa:rdgs:">x</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:latinLit:phi1103.phi001.lascivaroma-lat1:66.3@nisi:rdgs:">x</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:latinLit:phi1103.phi001.lascivaroma-lat1:67.2@cadmi:rdgs:">x</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:latinLit:phi1103.phi001.lascivaroma-lat1:68.31@arrectos:rdgs:">x</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:latinLit:phi1103.phi001.lascivaroma-lat1:70.2@libum:rdgs:">x</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:latinLit:phi1103.phi001.lascivaroma-lat1:70.3@inguen:rdgs:">x</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:latinLit:phi1103.phi001.lascivaroma-lat1:70.10@famelicorum:rdgs:">x</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:latinLit:phi1103.phi001.lascivaroma-lat1:72.1@pomari:rdgs:">x</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:latinLit:phi1103.phi001.lascivaroma-lat1:72.2@minare:rdgs:">x</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:latinLit:phi1103.phi001.lascivaroma-lat1:74.1@medios:rdgs:">x</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:latinLit:phi1103.phi001.lascivaroma-lat1:78@VARIANTI BELLISSIME DI CUNNILINGE:rdgs:">x</comment>
			<comment ref="urn:cts:latinLit:phi1103.phi001.lascivaroma-lat1:78@VARIANTI BELLISSIME DI CUNNILINGE:rdgs:">x</comment>
			 <comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg003.perseus-grc2:590@μέγαν-590@χόλον:rdgs:μελάγκολος">μελάγ-χολος, ον, dipped in black bile, ἰοί S.Tr.573. melagxolia!
In luogo di ‘non sei in grado di deporre la grande ira del cuore’ diventa ‘non sei in grado di lasciar perdere il ‘melancholos’ del cuore’. 
Cf Trachinie 572-577: ἐὰν γὰρ ἀμφίθρεπτον αἷμα τῶν ἐμῶν / σφαγῶν ἐνέγκῃ χερσίν, ᾗ μελάγχολος / ἔβαψεν ἰὸς θρέμμα Λερναίας ὕδρας, / ἔσται φρενός σοι τοῦτο κηλητήριον / τῆς Ἡρακλείας, ὥστε μήτιν’ εἰσιδὼν / στέρξει γυναῖκα κεῖνος ἀντὶ σοῦ πλέον.
Melagcholos oltre che da Sofocle (dove non c’è connotazione di ira) è usato dal greco tardo: Polluce Onomastico 6 124 (124)   Ὀργίλος, ὑπέρθυμος βαρύθυμος, ἄμετρος ὀργήν, τραχὺς ὀργήν, ἔκμετρος, χολώδης ἐπίχολος ἀκρόχολος μελάγχολος, ὀξύθυμος, ὀξυθυμίας, πικρός, δύσκολος, μεμψίμοιρος, ὠμός, ἀσυγγνώμων
</comment>
<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg003.perseus-grc2:0.27@παρὰ-0.27@Νεόφρονος:rdgs:">Neofrono (che, dice l’ipotesi, avrebbe messo in scena una Medea prima di Euripide), è cambiato in quello che sembra un nome parlante da A. Diventa invece locuzione avverbiale in Hn, mentre il modello comune di P e AG598 scrive un composto inattestato. La divisione è forse pan-aio-fronos?</comment>
<comment ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg003.perseus-grc2:0.27@παρὰ-0.27@Νεόφρονος:rdgs:">Neofrono (che, dice l’ipotesi, avrebbe messo in scena una Medea prima di Euripide), è cambiato in quello che sembra un nome parlante da A. Diventa invece locuzione avverbiale in Hn, mentre il modello comune di P e AG598 scrive un composto inattestato. La divisione è forse pan-aio-fronos?</comment>

  		</body>
  	</text>
  </TEI>